William Rivera Papers
William Rivera Papers
circa 1980-2010
Rivera, William McLeod, 1934-
3 linear ft.
American adult education practitioner and scholar in agricultural extension, education and training. Collection contains writings, printed materials, small amount of memorabilia.
2746185
Biographical History
William Rivera (1934- ) is an American adult education practitioner and scholar, specializing in international adult and agricultural extension education.
For nearly 40 years Rivera was a Professor in the College of Agriculture and Natural Resources at the University of Maryland, College Park. He is the author or editor of numerous books, reports and articles, and has extensive international experience with organizations like UNESCO, the Organization of American States (OAS), the Organization of Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), and World Education Inc. He has consulted for the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO/UN), the International Fund for Agricultural Development (IFAD), the U.N. Development Program (UNDP), the U.S. Agency for International Development (USAID), the World Bank, and more than twenty countries from Bolivia to Zambia.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The William Rivera Papers consists of personal files, subject files and writings.
Personal files contains biographical material (resumes, c.v.'s, personal statements on teaching and other topics), an award from the Association for International Agricultural Extension and Education (AIAEE), and a few items of memorabilia.
Subject files consists of Rivera's research files; topics include innovation in agriculture, innovation systems, rural knowledge economies, and correspondence from the Gates Foundation soliciting Rivera's expertise. Many of the folders contain papers by other authors as well as drafts, notes, partial papers and other material by Rivera.
The bulk of the collection consists of Rivera's Writings, including book chapters, introductions and drafts; work done as a consultant for USAID and the UN's Food and Agriculture Organization; course notes; papers; presentations and speeches; and a few items of published material. Except for the published material, all the writing is in typescript form, most of it printed from electronic files, and many are annotated by Rivera. Many are policy-related, focusing on reform in post-secondary agricultural extension; countries and regions represented include Egypt, France, India, Uganda, and sub-Saharan Africa.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into personal files, subject files and writings. Within each series, material is arranged alphabetically by title or topic. Where possible, presentations have been united with their related paper; if this could not be ascertained, the presentation was filed separately.
Related Material
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Rivera, William McLeod, 1934-; Agricultural education -- Developing countries.; Agricultural extension work -- Africa.; Agricultural extension work -- Contracting out.; Agricultural extension work -- India.; Agricultural extension work -- United States.; Adult education.; Educators.; Non-formal education.; Rural development -- Developing countries.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of William Rivera, 2001, 2011.
Inventory
- Personal files
  - Awards, AIAEE nomination and plaque (Box 1)
  - Biographical material, resumes, c.v.'s, "Perspectives on teaching," personal statement, more (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, few pieces of correspondence (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Addis Innovation Conference, includes correspondence with Kristen Davis about a presentation (Box 1)
  - AGNR 400 development models (Box 1)
  - AGNR 450 The agriculture workforce in the 21st century (Box 1)
  - AgX computer program (Box 1)
  - Best fit vs. best practices (Box 1)
  - Education/agriculture metaphors (Box 1)
  - Enabling agricultural innovation (Box 1)
  - Enabling evolution of agricultural knowledge systems (Box 1)
  - Ethiopia Strategy Support Program (ESSP), paper by David Colman and John W. Mellor (Box 1)
  - Gates Foundation, correspondence (Box 1)
  - Human resources development (HRD) (Box 2)
  - Innovation, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Innovation systems theory (Box 2)
  - Knowledge imperative (Box 2)
  - Post-secondary agricultural education and training (PSAET), includes material on sub-Saharan Africa (Box 2)
  - Program planning (Box 2)
  - Rural knowledge economies, includes "On the outskirts of the learning society" notes and drafts, and "On the outskirts of development" (rural females in sub-Saharan Africa) notes and drafts (Box 2)
  - System model controversies (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous graphics and illustrations (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous manuscript material, mostly unattributed typescripts, fragments; one or two handwritten items (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous photocopies, photocopies of articles, clippings, etc. (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous published material, heavily annotated copy of The Education of Adults: A World Perspective by John Lowe; annotated articles, booklets, etc.; 2 folders (Box 3)
- Writings
  - Books
    - Agricultural extension worldwide: Issues, practices and emerging priorities, Rivera and Schram, ed.s, presentation on a book edited by Rivera and Susan G. Schram; also includes acknowledgements, table of contents, and a review of the book by Kathiravelu K. Navaratnam (Box 3)
    - Agricultural extension reforms: Privatization and the public sector, annotated on first page with "my book" and "unfinished" (Box 3)
  - Consulting work
    - Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO) (Box 3)
      Includes the following:
      Agricultural extension worldwide: Policies and strategies for reform
      Agricultural knowledge extension systems: Policies and strategies for reform (course outline)
      Institutional needs assessments for agricultural research, technology development and extension in the Near East and North Africa region: Agricultural extension (with Ali Mohayed Bannaga)
    - USAID, on Agricultural Education and Training (AET) (Box 3)
      Introductory remarks
      Literature review of agricultural education and training
      Concept paper #1: Expanding and transforming AET
      Concept paper #2: "Spectrum of Ideas"
      Opportunities to develop innovative agricultural education
      Opportunities and pitfalls USAID should pay special attention to (response to "Opportunities" summary, by P. Tamboli)
      Outline of recommendations
      Review and comments on Module 4: Agricultural education and training (AET) for AIS
      Renewing investment in agricultural education and training (draft of paper)
  - Course notes
    - Agricultural extension decentralization and privatization, course outline, University of Maryland (Box 4)
    - Agricultural extension in transition worldwide: Policies and strategies for reform, written like a paper, but clearly states it is an overview of a course (Box 4)
    - Agricultural research and extension linkages, staff training course, University of Maryland (Box 4)
    - International agricultural extension and development, intensive 1-week course developed for l'Universite Catholique de Lille, France (Box 4)
    - Policy development and adult education, Fall 1980; ATE 600, Syracuse University (Box 4)
    - Progress, evolution and development, AGRI 632 (Box 4)
  - Papers
    - Adult education: An international perspective, Fall 1982; prepared for Continuing Education Association conference (Box 4)
    - Agricultural extension as adult education: Institutional evolution as forces for change, March 1991; presented at the Comparative and International Education Society conference, Pittsburgh (Box 4)
    - * Agricultural extension: The problems and politics of extending knowledge, author not given; presumed to be Rivera (Box 4)
    - Agricultural extension system reform and the challenges ahead (Box 4)
    - Agricultural extension in transition worldwide: Structural, financial and managerial reform strategies, June 1995; published in Public Administration and Development (UK), vol. 16, 1996; second version labeled "Introductiory chapter" (Box 4)
    - * Agricultural extension worldwide: Concepts and controversies, author not given; presumed to be Rivera (Box 4)
    - Agricultural higher education in sub-Saharan Africa: Challenges and opportunities, "original draft" (Box 4)
    - Agricultural knowledge and development in a new age and a different world, 2 versions, one presented in Mexico, date and event not specified, the other for publication (Box 4)
    - The challenge to develop an innovative agricultural sector (Box 4)
    - The challenge to develop an innovative nation (Box 4)
    - China's rural development and the food security challenge, October 2003; presented at the Institute for Global Chinese Affairs seminar, University of Maryland (Box 4)
    - Comparative agricultural extension systems, 1989; with Joseph Seepersad and Douglas H. Pletsch; published in Foundations and Changing Practices of Extension, D.J. Blackburn (ed.) (Box 4)
    - Contracting for agricultural extension: Good practices worldwide (Box 4)
    - Contracting for agricultural extension: Review and analysis of diverse public/private contracting arrangements worldwide, with Gary Alex (Box 4)
    - Contrasting perspectives and their reflection in current extension concepts and trends (Box 4)
    - The cooperative extension system (Box 4)
    - Decentralizing agricultural extension: Alternative strategies, published in the International Journal of Lifelong Education, 16:5, Sept-Oct 1997 (Box 4)
    - Developing agricultural extension systems nationwide: A structural approach (Box 4)
    - Enabling agriculture: The evolution and promise of agricultural knowledge frameworks, May 2006; with Regina Birner, Gary Alex and James Hanson; several versions, including printouts of powerpoint slides (Box 4)
    - Enabling agriculture: An innovative approach to link agricultural knowledge systems, with Regina Birner, Gary Alex and James Hanson (Box 4)
    - Enabling agriculture: From institutional innovations to the institution of innovation, with Regina Birner, Gary Alex and James Hanson (Box 4)
    - Extension reform: The challenges ahead, with Gary Alex (Box 4)
    - Facilitating innovation: Evolving frameworks for investment in agricultural development, several versions, including first draft with alternate subtitle; one says it was delivered as a keynote address, but event and date are not given (Box 5)
    - Good practices in contracting for extension, with Willem Zijp (Box 5)
    - Guidelines for successful agricultural extension, October 1989; prepared for the American Association of Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE) conference, Atlantic City (Box 5)
    - Human resources development in the agriculture sector: A policy perspective (Box 5)
    - Human resources development for modernizing the agricultural workforce, with Gary Alex (Box 5)
    - In a new age, new challenges require new thinking, September 2008; National Federation of Coffee Growers of Columbia seminar on science and tropical agriculture for the 21st century, Bogota (Box 5)
    - Indian Center for Modern Agriculture, concept paper; on efforts by GTZ (German Technical Corporation); includes printout of powerpoint slides (Box 5)
    - Innovation: Ideas in progress, March 2007; presented at the 5th Global Consortium of Higher Education and Research (GCHERA) (Box 5)
    - International program development and cross-cultural evaluation: The world of illiteracy, 1982; prepared for the Evaluation Research Society/ENET annual conference, Baltimore (Box 5)
    - The invisible frontier: The current limits of decentralization and privatization in developing countries, March 2000; revision of paper presented at the Association for International Agricultural and Extension Education (AIAEE), Arlington, VA and later published (Box 5)
    - The knowledge imperative: Post-secondary training vis-à-vis higher education, abstract only (Box 5)
    - The knowledge imperative and a workforce educational network (Box 5)
    - Learning is at the center: A recommendation to the World Bank regarding the development of Agricultural Knowledge Services (Box 5)
    - A major challenge to agricultural development: Determining a policy strategy for agricultural extension, outline for policy paper (Box 5)
    - Making agriculture work as a business for the poor: Uganda's stragies to reform its agricultural research, extension and education systems (Box 5)
    - Market access and farmer education: Parternship farming -- a new approach to enable agriculture, on efforts by GTZ (German Technical Corporation) (Box 5)
    - The market-link imperative: Refocusing public sector extension, published in Journal of International Agricultural Education and Extension, 16:2, Summer 2009 (Box 5)
    - The missing link: Challenge to develop smallholders as professionals and agripreneurs, January 2010; keynote address at Green Week Scientific Conference, Berlin; includes draft and final paper and printout of powerpoint (Box 5)
    - Opportunities to develop innovative agricultural education (Box 5)
    - An overview of agricultural extension systems: The territory, recent developments and recommended directions, June 1988; presented at IFAD Seminar on Generation and Transfer of Technnology for Poor Small Farmers", Seoul (Box 5)
    - Policy considerations for reform of public sector agricultural extension systems: A framework for analysis (Box 5)
    - Private sector participation in extension, includes printout of powerpoint (Box 5)
    - Production and beyond: Refocusing public sector extension (Box 5)
    - PSAET system challenges: Focus on sub-Saharan Africa (Box 5)
    - Public policy development game: Basic concepts, 2 versions; handwritten on first page of one is "AEED 7892" (Box 5)
    - The public sector agricultural extension system in Egypt: A pluralistic complex in transition, published in Journal of International Agricultural Education and Extension, Fall 1997 (Box 5)
    - Reinventing agricultural extension: Fiscal system reform, decentralization and privatization, 3 versions (Box 5)
    - System model controversies: Conceptual and ethical challenges in the reform of public sector agricultural extension, 2 versions; earlier title, "A wealth of extension approaches" (Box 6)
    - Taking sides: Perspectives that shape extension's organization and practice, Top of page 1 says, "Chapter" (Box 6)
    - Three post-secondary agricultural education and training challenges and the concept of "workforce education systems", published in Journal of Agricultural Education and Extension, 13:1, Jan/Feb 2008 (Box 6)
    - Transforming post-secondary agricultural education and training by design: Solutions for sub-Saharan Africa, multiple versions; commissioned by World Bank; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Whither agricultural extension worldwide?, 1998; original and later revision; prepared for conference on Knowledge Generation and Transfer: Implications for Agriculture in the 21st Century, Berkely (Box 6)
    - The World Bank's view of lifelong learning: Handmaiden of the market, several versions (Box 6)
  - Presentations and speeches
    - An alternative view of post-secondary agricultural education: Workforce development, printout of powerpoint (Box 6)
    - Beyond production: Agricultural knowledge systems and knowledge advancement, "Ag, Ed & Inno Book" (Box 6)
    - Contracting for agricultural extension services, with input from Willem Zijp and Gary Alex; printout of powerpoint (Box 6)
    - Contracting for delivery of extension education and advisory services (Box 6)
    - The development of an agricultural innovation system: COFUPRO, printout of powerpoint (Box 6)
    - Enabling agriculture: From institutional innovations to the institution of innovation, with Regina Birner, Gary Alex and James Hanson; printout of powerpoint (Box 6)
    - Facilitating innovation: Initiatives in extension, printout of powerpoint (Box 6)
    - Forces shaping agrcultural knowledge support systems, printout of powerpoint (Box 6)
    - Global developments shaping extension, September 2000; printout of powerpoint; presented at 50th Jubilee of the University of Hohenheim (Box 6)
    - Global reform of agricultural extension for rural development, printout of powerpoint (Box 6)
    - Global reforms and agricultural extension: Trends and the public sector, 1998; text to accompany overheads; prepared for Knowledge Generation and Transfer: Implications for Agriculture in the 21st Century, Berkeley (Box 6)
    - Pathways and tensions in the family of reform, September 2007; keynote address at 18th European Seminar on Extension Education (ESEE), Prague (Box 6)
    - Public policy: Concepts for educators of adults, 1984; keynote address for Policy-Making and Policy Education Washington Workshop for Extension Specialists (Box 6)
    - World Food Summit, appears to be opening remarks or introduction, edited possibly for later publication (Box 6)
  - Published material
    - Journal articles, reprints of articles from International Journal of Lifelong Education; clippings from Journal of Extension Services, Continuing Higher Education, Lifelong Learning: The Adult Years (Box 6)
    - Papers/reports, "Comparative Extension: CES, TES, T&V, and FSR/D," Occasional Paper #1 from Center for International Extension Development (CIED); "Contracting for Extension," World Bank Agricultural Knowledge and Information Systems (AKIS) Good Practice Note (Box 6)